<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Sam Lewis</title><link href="http://www.samlewis.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.samlewis.me/feeds/04.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.samlewis.me/</id><updated>2016-04-21T23:15:41+10:00</updated><entry><title>Getting started with the xv6 operating system Date: 2016-04-18 Slug: getting-started-xv6</title><link href="http://www.samlewis.me/2016/04/getting-started-with-the-xv6-operating-system-date-2016-04-18-slug-getting-started-xv6" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-04-21T23:15:41+10:00</published><author><name>Sam Lewis</name></author><id>tag:www.samlewis.me,2016-04-21:2016/04/getting-started-with-the-xv6-operating-system-date-2016-04-18-slug-getting-started-xv6</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;xv6 is a nifty operating system that is essentially a reimplementation of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Version_6_Unix"&gt;Sixth Edition Unix&lt;/a&gt; that, unlike most of the huge montholithic Linux or BSD distributions that you'd run on your workstation or server, is simple enough to be used as a learning tool. Though xv6 lacks in functionality that you'd expect from a modern operating system, much of the core unix concepts and structure remain the same. xv6 is also very lightweight, only taking a few seconds to compile and allows remote debugging. This all makes it great for understanding how modern operating systems hang together. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, xv6 was developed by MIT as a teaching operating system for their &lt;a href="https://pdos.csail.mit.edu/6.828/2014/xv6.html"&gt;6.828 course&lt;/a&gt;. The course page for 6.828 is a great resource that MIT are kind enough to have publicly avaliable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MIT also produce a fantastic &lt;a href="https://pdos.csail.mit.edu/6.828/2014/xv6/book-rev8.pdf"&gt;xv6 reference book&lt;/a&gt; that provides commentary on the structure of the xv6 operating system. Additionally, the xv6 source actually self documents - the xv6 &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt; file contains a target (&lt;code&gt;make xv6.pdf&lt;/code&gt;) that generates a &lt;a href="https://pdos.csail.mit.edu/6.828/2014/xv6/xv6-rev8.pdf"&gt;pdf of the source code&lt;/a&gt;, which amazingly comes in under 100 pages and 10k lines of source (including comments!). Not bad for an entire, functional, operating system. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;xv6 is typically run virtualized using qemu on a Linux host machine. To get started with xv6, clone the xv6 repo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;git clone git://github.com/mit-pdos/xv6-public.git xv6
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then to start it as a virtual machine under qemu:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;cd xv6
make qemu
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If make fails, make sure you have your compiler toolchain installed. There's some good info on the &lt;a href="https://pdos.csail.mit.edu/6.828/2014/tools.html"&gt;6.282 tools page&lt;/a&gt;. For me, on Fedora, I needed to install gcc with &lt;code&gt;dnf install gcc&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have your compiler toolchain working, qemu will pop up and you'll be presented with the xv6 shell. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="qemu xv6 shell" src="qemu.png" /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From here, you'll be able to run a few simple commands like &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;cat&lt;/code&gt; and revel in the knowledge that you can understand what's happening behind the covers by reading through the source code for the shell - line 8500 in the source code listing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core &lt;code&gt;while&lt;/code&gt; loop the shell executes is shown below. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; // Read and run input commands.
 while(getcmd(buf, sizeof(buf)) &amp;gt;= 0){
    if(buf[0] == ’c’ &amp;amp;&amp;amp; buf[1] == ’d’ &amp;amp;&amp;amp; buf[2] == ’ ’){
        // Clumsy but will have to do for now.
        // Chdir has no effect on the parent if run in the child.
        buf[strlen(buf)−1] = 0; // chop \n

        if(chdir(buf+3) &amp;lt; 0)
            printf(2, &amp;quot;cannot cd %s\n&amp;quot;, buf+3);
        continue;
    }
    if(fork1() == 0)
        runcmd(parsecmd(buf));
    wait();
 }
 exit();
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This loop gets a command from a user, checks if it's the &lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; command and attempts to change directory if it is, otherwise it forks, and runs the entered command in the child process. I personally love how simple and enjoyable the code is to read - check out the rest of the listing for &lt;code&gt;sh.c&lt;/code&gt; in the xv6 source code pdf - it's only 400 pages of code and a delight to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was only a brief peek and excitement builder for xv6 - there's so many other facets that are worth having a deeper dive into. Join next time when I'll explore the xv6 bootstrap sequence!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>